alitalia.com 2014-12-20

# Alitalia Privacy | Alitalia

POLICY AND CONSENT TO THE USE OF PERSONAL DATA, PURSUANT TO LEGISLATIVE DECREE NO. 196 OF JUNE 30, 2003, ART. 13 

Alitalia Compagnia Aerea Italiana S.p.A. ("Alitalia S.p.A.") handles all of its customer data according to the legislation referred to in Italian legislative decree no. 196 of June 30, 2003, regarding the "Personal data protection code," which implements the European Union directives on this subject in Italy. 

Alitalia S.p.A. ensures that the processing of personal data—however it is obtained—is performed with respect for fundamental rights and freedoms, as well as the individual's dignity, with particular reference to confidentiality, personal identity and the right to personal data protection. This policy is not valid for data collected through Alitalia's partner websites, which may be accessed using links on the Alitalia website, for which the company is not responsible in any way. For such processing, a separate policy should be provided by the respective owners. 

For security reasons, we are required, to an increasing extent, to notify the various local authorities worldwide—the immigration and customs service in particular—of our customers' personal and travel data, obtained as part of normal flight schedules; as well as in Italy where requested by the Central Directorate for Immigration and Border Police. This notification is required in order to implement the contract of carriage. 

Furthermore, measures taken to ensure data confidentiality comply with the provisions set out in the opinions of the Working Group Art. 29 for Personal Data Protection no. 2/2007 of February 15, 2007, reviewed and updated on June 24, 2008, on the information for passengers concerning the transfer of PNR data to the United States authorities (for more details, please see Information for Passengers Traveling to the United States). 

Please carefully refer to this page regularly to check for any necessary updates or revisions, as well as to adopt and/or conform to national, community or international legislation, or to adapt to technological innovations. 

Updates will be reported on this web page and will remain visible at all times, so that anyone who wishes to do so can be fully informed about the use of their own personal data through the Alitalia website or through other different data collection channels. 

We recommend looking at this page every time you visit the Alitalia website.

DATA PROCESSING AND METHODS 

Personal data processing will occur with guaranteed security and confidentiality and may be performed not only with manual tools but also using automatic tools (both computer and telematic) capable of storing, managing and transmitting the same data. Personal data will be: processed in a legal and proper manner; collected and recorded for specific, explicit, legitimate and precise purposes, and, if necessary, updated, relevant and complete purposes, not exceeding the purposes of processing; stored in a way that allows it to be identified by the individual for a period of time not exceeding that necessary for the purposes for which it was collected or subsequently processed.

DATA PROVIDED VOLUNTARILY BY THE USER 

Alitalia collects personal information and other data that is communicated through the Company's call center or voluntarily entered into registration forms on the website and the Mobile site, as well as optional and explicit data submitted to the Company by post or email. This data may be information that is necessary for providing the services requested by the individual (primarily the air transport service), or other services (e.g. newsletter) and/or for contacting the individual (name, address, any other personal data entered in the letter). The optional, explicit and voluntary sending of emails to addresses indicated on this website, implies the subsequent gathering of the sender's email address—which is necessary for responding to requests—as well as any other personal data entered in the letter.

BROWSING DATA COLLECTED BY USING ELECTRONIC TOOLS 

The computer systems and software procedures used to operate the Alitalia S.p.A. website and Mobile site acquire, over the course of their normal use, a series of personal information, the transmission of which is implicit in the use of Internet communication protocols (e.g. the user's IP address or the domain name of the computer used to access the website, the URL of the requested resources, the time of the request or the session time, the method used to submit the query to the server, the size of the files received in response to the request, the numerical code concerning the response status given by the server and other types of information regarding the user's operating system and computing environment).

COOKIES 

While browsing the Alitalia S.p.A. website, information will be collected that allows your computer or browser to be identified using files called "cookies." "Cookies" are strings of encrypted text that can be stored on the user's cell phone (if accessing the Mobile site) or computer, so they can be quickly identified at a later date. Cookies for the Mobile site, only store data relating to Name, Surname and Ticket Number. Cookies on computers allow websites to be personalized, making navigation easier for the user and—by quantitatively checking access to various web pages—allowing better presentation of the most requested information. The cookies we use do not store personal data, except for the IP address. The rest of the information stored in the cookies will remain anonymous, since the cookie's identification number is not associated with the personal data provided by the user. You can always request that the cookies are disabled, by modifying your browser settings.

DATA COLLECTED THROUGH THE CALL CENTER 

Calls made to the call center numbers listed in the Alitalia website may involve processing the user's personal data, with the aim of providing the services requested by the user, such as: bookings, purchases and dispatch of tickets for air transport requested by the passenger, changes to or replacements for tickets that have already been issued, reimbursements, post-sales assistance, special assistance and purchases of additional flight services, etc.   
Finalizing electronic transactions may involve collecting data from our customers' credit cards, which will be processed with all the necessary precautions set out in the relevant legislation. Alitalia may also use third-party call centers that operate—always in full respect of privacy regulations—with a special service contract on behalf of the Owner, as external data processors pursuant to Art. 29 of Legislative Decree no. 196 of June 30, 2003. If the third-party call centers process data owned by Alitalia outside the EU, Alitalia asks the suppliers to respect the safeguards provided for by Directive 95/46/EC and subsequent European Commission Decisions.

PURPOSE OF COLLECTION 

Through the website, Alitalia collects personal data from its users, which is required for putting in place the authorization, qualification and personalization operations of access to the different areas and relative content of the Company's website.   
As specified, Alitalia S.p.A. collects the data required for complying with the contractual obligations to customers and that from passenger ticket booking and purchasing operations, from the provision of ancillary services, as well as the data required for managing reports and complaints sent by customers and for the other purposes described above. The fulfillment of these obligations implies that this data must be available to those in charge of Alitalia operating and commercial functions, as well as partner carriers implementing various commercial agreements and, where necessary, insurance companies with which Alitalia has taken out the mandatory or optional coverages related to executing air transport services and connected services.   
The personal and/or sensitive data provided or collected throughout the contractual relationship may be communicated, in accordance with and within the limits of the requested service, to:

  * parties within the Alitalia S.p.A. facility for the purposes of improved performance, parties appointed as data processors by Alitalia S.p.A. pursuant to the procedures set out in Legislative Decree 196/2003;
  * parties outside the Alitalia S.p.A. facility, which perform functions that are strictly connected or instrumental to our business, functions that must be considered fundamental to Alitalia's operations.

Any sensitive data may be also processed without the individual's explicit consent in the cases of Art. 26, note 4, Legislative Decree 196/2003. However, this data will not be disclosed. It must be noted that in some cases (not subject to the ordinary administration of this website) the Authority can request news and information pursuant to Art. 157 of Legislative Decree no. 196/2003, for the purposes of controlling personal data processing. In these cases, the response is mandatory, under penalty of a fine. Alitalia S.p.A., as "Data Controller," informs you that the data in question will be processed and used exclusively for the purposes outlined in this policy.

ACCESS THROUGH SOCIAL NETWORKS 

Please also note that members of the MilleMiglia Program (hereinafter the "Program"), who intend to join the Alitalia Social Login service, that personal data provided when joining the service (hereinafter the "Service") will be collected and recorded by Alitalia S.p.A. on paper, electronic and/or computer and/or telematic formats, protected and processed with the appropriate means for ensuring security and confidentiality in accordance with the provisions of the Code. Please note that the data provided directly when joining or indirectly through Social Networks may be used for purposes strictly connected and instrumental to participation in the Program and/or joining the Program itself, as well as personalization of Services designed by Alitalia S.p.A for subscribing customers. Upon customer consent, the data provided may be used by Alitalia S.p.A. for promotional, advertising and marketing purposes, such as sending advertising, promotional and informational material on products and services, as well as for direct statistical analyses for detecting the degree of satisfaction for services and products offered. Please note that customers can easily exercise their rights set out in Art. 7 and subsequent of Legislative Decree no. 196/2003 (including, but not limited to, the rights to obtain confirmation of the existence of data about them and the communication of said data in an intelligible form, the source of the data, the purposes and methods of processing, updating, correcting or integrating data, deletion, anonymization or blocking of personal data processed illegally, and the right to object, in whole or in part, to its use) by sending a formal request to the following email address: privacy@alitalia.it.

EXERCISING RIGHTS 

Alitalia S.p.A. customers can contact the Data Controller and/or the Data Processor to assert their rights as provided for by Art. 7 "Right to access personal data and other rights" of Legislative Decree 196/2003 no. 196. To exercise these rights, send an email to the following address: privacy@alitalia.it.   
Please note that requests of a different nature (e.g. complaints, refund requests, requests regarding the MilleMiglia Program, etc.) sent to the privacy address will not be taken into account. For any such requests, please use the dedicated telephone numbers and addresses (e.g. see page: Contacts or Post-flight Assistance or the MilleMiglia section). If you no longer wish to receive communications from the Alitalia Group, please follow the following procedures:

  * For sales communications from Alitalia, click the cancellation link at the bottom of all emails from Alitalia. Cancellation may take several minutes. Please wait for confirmation that the operation has ended, before leaving the relevant web page. The data will be canceled within five days of the cancellation request
  * For communications to MilleMiglia Members, please access the "Your Profile" service, selecting "No communication" in the Communication section of "News and Offers", and click "Update." Or, you can call Customer Service. Your profile will be updated within five days of the request.

DATA CONTROLLER AND DATA PROCESSOR 

The Data Controller is Alitalia S.p.A.   
with its registered office at Piazza Almerico da Schio   
Pal. RPU   
00054   
Fiumicino (RM), Italy 

The internal data processors of Alitalia S.p.A. are:

  * Deputy General Manager Business
  * Deputy General Manager Corporate
  * Chief Commercial Officer
  * Senior Vice President of Information Systems and Telecommunications
  * Senior Vice President of Security
  * Senior Vice President of General Counsel
  * Human Resources Director
  * Purchasing and Services Director
  * Auditing Director
